<section id="deploy">
  <title>Deploying Rex</title>
  <para>
    This chapter describes how to configure and run Rex.
  </para>

  <section>
    <title>First Time Configuration</title>
    <para>
      Before running Rex for the first time, there are a few steps you
      need to take.  Rex requires access to a database.  Currently,
      Rex supports PostgreSQL <xref linkend="bib-postgres"/> and
      Microsft SQL Server.  This database is where RETS data is
      stored, as well as Rex specific information.  Rex requires
      read/write access to the database, as well as the ability to
      create new tables.
    </para>

    <section>
      <title>PostgreSQL Setup</title>
      <para>
        PostgreSQL must be configured to accept TCP/IP connections, as
        this is how the JDBC driver connects.  This is done adding the
        following setting in <filename>postgresql.conf</filename>:
      </para>
      <programlisting>tcpip_socket = true
</programlisting>
      <para>
        You may also have to edit <filename>pg_hba.conf</filename> to
        make network connections permissible.  See the documentation
        in that file for details.
      </para>
      <para>
        It is probably a good idea to create a user other than the
        default <literal>postgres</literal> superuser.  This user must
        have read and write access, and permissions to create new
        tables in the database used by Rex.
      </para>
      <para>
        The JDBC driver for Postgres version 7.4.x is included with
        the distribution.
      </para>
    </section>
      
    <section>
      <title>Microsoft SQL Server Setup</title>
      <para>
        First, either choose an existing database, or create a new
        database for use with Rex.  Then, create a new user that has
        the following role memberships:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><literal>public</literal></listitem>
        <listitem><literal>db_owner</literal></listitem>
        <listitem><literal>db_datareader</literal></listitem>
        <listitem><literal>db_datawriter</literal></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        There are currently no free or Open Source SQL Server JDBC
        drivers, so none is included with Rex.  The one that Microsoft
        offers is buggy and does not work with Rex.  The only
        supported driver is the commercial JSQLConnect driver from
        JNetDirect <xref linkend="bib-jnetdirect"/>.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Installing a JDBC Driver</title>
      <para>
        The easiest way to install your JDBC driver is to use the
        Administration Tool.  Choose the Install Jar command from the
        File menu.  You must then restart the Administration Tool
        and/or Rex to use the new JDBC driver.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Configuring Database Properties</title>
      <para>
        From the Configuration tab of the Administration Tool, the
        current database properties are listed.  You will have change
        these to suit your environment.  Click on the Edit button, to
        bring up the Database Properties dialog, as in <xref
        linkend="fig-db"/>.  You should use the Test Connection button
        to make sure that the properties are entered correctly.  If
        the test fails, then neither the Administration Tool nor Rex
        will be able to access your database.
      </para>
      <figure id="fig-db">
        <title>Database Properties Window</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="db.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Creating the Schema</title>
      <para>
        Rex needs tables for it's own use, such as user information.
        Before you create users and groups, you need to create these
        tables by chosing the Create Schema command from the Database
        menu.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section> <!-- First Time -->

  <section>
    <title>Configuring RETS Parameters</title>
    <para>
      From the main Configuration panel, as seen in <xref
                                                       linkend="fig-config"/>, you can configure various RETS
      parameters.
    </para>
    <figure id="fig-config">
      <title>Configuration Tab</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="config.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      The Listening Port is the TCP port number that the Rex server
      listens on.  6103 is the standard, well-known port number for
      RETS.  The Metadata Directory points to the root directory of
      the metadata hierarchy.  Configuring metadata is explained in
      <xref linkend="deploy-metadata"/>.  The Image Root and Image
      Pattern parameters are used to allow Rex to serve up images for
      the GetObject transaction.  The Image Root is a directory where
      the images are located.  The Image Pattern is a percent
      substitution pattern that describes the format of the actual
      file names.  The possible patterns and their substitutions are
      listed in <xref linkend="tab-image-pattern"/>.
    </para>

    <table frame="all" id="tab-image-pattern">
      <title>Image Patterns</title>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Pattern</entry>
            <entry>Substitution</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>%k</entry>
            <entry>Object Key</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>%i</entry>
            <entry>Object Index</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>%I</entry>
            <entry>Object Index, or empty if index is 0</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para>
      For example, if you have pictures
      in <filename>/home/rex/pictures/</filename>.  The key is used as
      the base file name, with each image given a number.  Say there
      are three pictures for the property
      ID <literal>LN1001</literal>, the full paths for these pictures
      are:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <literal>/home/rex/pictures/LN1001_1.jpg</literal>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <literal>/home/rex/pictures/LN1001_2.jpg</literal>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <literal>/home/rex/pictures/LN1001_3.jpg</literal>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      The, you could set the Image Root
      to <filename>/home/rex/pictures</filename> and the Image Pattern
      to <literal>%k_%i.jpg</literal>.  The <literal>%k</literal> gets
      replaced with the object ID, and the <literal>%i</literal> gets
      replaced with the image number.
    </para>
    <para>
      The <literal>%k</literal> percent pattern may be proceeded by a
      number modifier that truncates the number of characters used
      during substitution.  This allows files to be split up into
      multiple directories for large installations.  If the number is
      positive, the characters are taken from the front, where if the
      number is negative, the characters are taken from the end. So,
      with a pattern of <literal>%-2k/%k_%i.jpg</literal>, the first
      picture
      for <literal>LN1001</literal>, <literal>LN1002</literal>, <literal>LN1101</literal>
      would be at the following paths:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <literal>/home/rex/pictures/01/LN1001_1.jpg</literal>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <literal>/home/rex/pictures/02/LN1002_1.jpg</literal>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <literal>/home/rex/pictures/01/LN1101_1.jpg</literal>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Users</title>
    <para>
      Users are managed through the Users Tab as seen in <xref
                                                            linkend="fig-users"/>.  Users may be created, removed, and
      edited from the User menu or contextual menu.  Users may also
      be added and removed from groups.
    </para>

    <figure id="fig-users">
      <title>Users Tab</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="users.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Groups</title>
    <para>
      Groups are manged through the Groups Tab as seen in <xref
      linkend="fig-groups"/>. Groups may be created and removed from
      the Group menu or contextual menu.
    </para>

    <figure id="fig-groups">
      <title>Groups Tab</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="groups.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>
      Group rules allow access to fields to be restricted for members
      of this group.  Rules are written for a particular resource and
      class.  There two types of rules: include and exlude.  Include
      rules includes on the fields listed.  Exclude rules includes all
      fields except the ones listed.  An example rule is shown in
      <xref linkend="fig-rule"/>.  The individual fields are listed
      with spaces between them.  If a user is a member of multiple
      groups, then the fields allowed to be seen are a union of the
      fields of each group's set of fields.
    </para>

    <figure id="fig-rule">
      <title>Rule Dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="rule.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section> <!-- Groups -->

  <section id="deploy-metadata">
    <title>Configuring Metadata</title>
    <para>
      Metadata describes how to map property data in your relational
      database to RETS names.  The metadata is stored as compact
      format metadata, split into multiple files.  For more
      information on compact metadata format, see RETS specification.
      A sample set of metadata is provided on the Rex website, and
      should be used as a starting point.
    </para>
  </section>
</section> <!-- deploy -->

<!--
Local Variables:
mode: xml
sgml-parent-document: ("manual.xml" "" "section")
End:
-->
