<section id="install">
  <title>Installation</title>
  <para>
    There are a number of installation options for &name;.  The
    easiest method is to us one of the standalone versions that use an
    embedded version of Apache Tomcat <xref linkend="bib-tomcat"/>.
    The only other requirements to run this version is Java <xref
    linkend="bib-java"/> 5.0 or higher and a relational database.  However, &name;
    is developed as a Java web application, so you can use your own
    application server, such as WebLogic, WebSphere, or Resin, if you
    already have licenses for one.
  </para>

  <section id="windows">
    <title>Windows Installation</title>
    <para>
      If you are running on Windows, a normal Windows installer is
      provided that installs into the Program Files directory.  You
      need to have Java installed prior to installing &name;.  The
      installer also adds items into the Start Menu and a Windows
      Service.  The Service can be used to start and stop the server,
      like any other Windows Service.  Before running &name;, you
      should first configure it.  There are a number of items that
      must be setup.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="non-windows">
    <title>Non-Windows Installation</title>
    <para>
      For other platforms, such as Linux and Mac OS X, a gzipped tar
      file is provided.  This archive does not contain any support for
      init scripts or startup items.  The &name; server is distributed
      as an executable Jar file.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="webapp">
    <title>Web Application Installation</title>
    <para>
      A version of &name; without Tomcat is available as a zip file or
      gzipped tar file.  This distribution includes only the web
      application and the administration tool.  An application server
      is required to run the web application.  However, only Java
      Servlets are used, so you do not need any other J2EE technology,
      like EJB.
    </para>

    <para>
      Depending on your application server, you will need to pick up the
      WEB-INF directory from the tar or zip file and place it in the
      appropriate place.
    </para>
  </section>
</section>

<!--
Local Variables:
mode: xml
sgml-parent-document: ("manual.xml" "" "section")
End:
-->
